

# Matthew Poland MS, PA-C Data Enthusiast

As an ICU clinician with 8 years of experience, I have cultivated a distinctive skill set that includes effective communication, critical thinking, adaptability, and teamwork within demanding situations. I am a firm believer in the transformative power of well-organized data to enhance the quality of patients' lives. Driven to transition into the field of Data Science, I have invested over a thousand hours in studying data preparation, statistical analysis, data visualization, and predictive models. Eager to embark on this new career path, I am enthusiastic about learning and proving myself as a valuable team contributor in an entry-level Data Science role.

matthewpoland@icloud.com — (973) 879-9407 — Jersey City, NJ — mattpolands.github.io

## **Experience**

Hackensack Meridian Health — 2015 to present Quality and Improvement Analyst — 2023 to present

- Conduct exploratory data analysis for the Trauma Quality Program to uphold Level 1 Trauma Center designation and implement ACS/NTDB/TQIP standards
- Record and extract reportable data into and from our Trauma Database and Epic (EHR) in accordance with HIPAA to research quality measures (time series analysis on injury epidemiology)
- Contribute to Medical Affairs by authoring and refining critical hospital network policies
- Perform literature reviews to write treatment guidelines
   Physician Assistant 2015 to present
- Organize and dynamically prioritize hundreds of daily objectives with patient care at the forefront while addressing the needs of consultant treatment plans, families, nursing care, and disposition plans
- Embrace an autonomous work environment when needed (depending on shift, make upwards of 90-100% of patient-care decisions)
- Manage a complex care team
- Distill and present complex health data to diverse audiences including diagnosis, treatment, prognosis, and palliative meetings
- Supervise and train clinicians in clinical management and presentation skills
- Recognized as Neurosurgical, Neurocritical Care, and Stroke Committee APP Liaison
- Awarded 2022 PA of the Year

Pratt Institute — 2012 to 2016
Institutional Advancement Operations Associate

- Utilized Blackbaud Raiser's Edge CRM software to manage our donor database
- Maintained a system of financial records to ensure accurate IA inter-department budgeting
- Connected companies with art students to offer unique philanthropic and joint marketing ventures

#### **Technical Skills**

Python, R, SQL, Tableau, Excel, NumPy, pandas, matplotlib, seaborn, PostgreSQL, pgAdmin, sci-kit learn, SciPy, Keras, Tensorflow, PyTorch, Colab, Jupyter, Git, Apache Pulsar

### **Data Science Certifications**

- Statistician in R (Enrolled)
- Machine Learning Scientist with Python (Enrolled)
- Practical Apache Pulsar Application Development
   2023
- Data Scientist with Python from Datacamp -2023
- Data Analyst with Python from Datacamp 2023
- Python for Data Science and Machine Learning from Pierian Training - 2023
- Machine Learning, Data Science and Generative
   Al with Python from Udemy 2023
- Math for Data Science Masterclass from Pierian Training - 2023
- Complete SQL from Pierian Training 2022

# **Healthcare Licenses/Certifications**

NCCPA and NJ PA License / ATLS, ENLS, ACLS, BLS

#### **Education**

- MIT | MicroMasters | Statistics and Data Science (Enrolled for 2024)
- SHU | Master of Science | Physician Assistant Studies - 2015
- SHU | Bachelor of Science | Business
   Administration (Finance/Marketing) 2007

#### **Projects**

- Dementia Prediction
- Global Burden of Disease